<eprints xmlns="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/1.1/eprints" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/1.1/eprints http://www.openarchives.org/OAI/1.1/eprints.xsd">
    <content>
        <text>Content Policy for types of document &amp; data set held 
1. This is an institutional or departmental repository.
2. SEDICI holds all types of materials.
3. Deposited items may include:
(a) working drafts
(b) submitted versions (as sent to journals for peer-review)
(c) accepted versions (authors final peer-reviewed drafts)
(d) published versions (publisher-created files)
4. Items are individually tagged with:
(a) their version type and date.
(b) their peer-review status.
(c) their publication status.
5. Principal Languages: Spanish; English; Portuguese</text>
    </content>
    <metadataPolicy>
        <text>1. Anyone may access the metadata free of charge.
2. The metadata may be re-used in any medium without prior permission and re-sold commercially provided the OAI Identifier or a link to the original metadata record are given.
3. For more information, please see webpage: http://sedici.unlp.edu.ar/pages/politicas</text>
    </metadataPolicy>
    <dataPolicy>
        <text>Data Policy for full-text and other full data items 
1. Anyone may access full items free of charge. 
2. Copies of full items generally can be: reproduced, and displayed or performed, provided
- the authors, title and full bibliographic details are given 
- a hyperlink and/or URL are given for the original metadata page 
3. Some full items are individually tagged with different rights permissions and conditions. 
4. For more information see webpage: http://sedici.unlp.edu.ar/.</text>
    </dataPolicy>
    <submissionPolicy>
        <text>Submission Policy concerning depositors, quality &amp; copyright 
1. Items may only be deposited by accredited members, academic staff, registered students, and employees of the institution, or their delegated agents.
2. Authors may only submit their own work for archiving.
3. The administrator only vets items for relevance to the scope of SEDICI, valid layout &amp; format, and the exclusion of spam
4. The validity and authenticity of the content of submissions is the sole responsibility of the depositor.
5. Items can be deposited at any time, but will not be made publicly visible until any publishers or funders embargo period has expired.
6. Any copyright violations are entirely the responsibility of the authors/depositors.
7. If SEDICI receives proof of copyright violation, the relevant item will be removed immediately.</text>
    </submissionPolicy>
    <comment>Preservation Policy 
1. Items will be retained indefinitely.
2. SEDICI will try to ensure continued readability and accessibility.
(a) Items will be migrated to new file formats where necessary.
3. SEDICI is working with external partners to backup items in external archives  
4. SEDICI regularly backs up its files according to current best practice.
5. The original bit stream is retained for all items, in addition to any upgraded formats.
6. Items may be removed at the request of the author/copyright holder, but this is strongly discouraged.
7. Acceptable reasons for withdrawal include:
(a) Journal publishers rules
(b) Proven copyright violation or plagiarism
(c) Legal requirements and proven violations
(d) National Security
(e) Falsified research
8. Withdrawn items are not deleted per se, but are removed from public view.
9. Withdrawn items identifiers/URLs are not retained.
10. URLs will continue to point to tombstone citations, to avoid broken links and to retain item histories.  
11. Errata and corrigenda lists may be included with the original record if required.
12. If necessary, an updated version may be deposited.
(a) The item s persistent URL will always link to the latest version.
13. Items are allocated a checksum to facilitate the detection of alterations.
14. No closure policy defined.</comment>
</eprints>