<document xmlns="http://di.tamu.edu/DRI/1.0/" xmlns:i18n="http://apache.org/cocoon/i18n/2.1" version="1.1">

<body>
<div id="file.about.div.about" n="about" rend="primary">
<head>About MOspace</head>

<p>MOspace is the digital institutional repository of the University of Missouri System, and is a joint
initiative of the University Libraries, the Office of Library Systems, and the Division of Information
Technology. It is a permanent digital storehouse of research and knowledge, focusing on works created by
those connected with the University of Missouri. MOspace is place where faculty, staff and students can
store their intellectual output, and depend upon a permanent URL.</p>

<p>MOspace allows the library to preserve and provide open access to items in a more
permanent way than posting to a website. The project uses <xref target="http://dspace.org/">DSpace</xref>,
an open source application developed at MIT, which provides permanent URLs for documents deposited
through it to the MOspace server. The Libraries are committed to this ongoing effort as part of the next
generation of library collections.</p>

<p>MOspace, in addition to acting as a preservation tool, is our part of the international open
access movement. You have probably heard of the recent votes in favor of open access by
<xref target="http://www.news.harvard.edu/gazette/2008/02.14/99-fasvote.html">Harvard's Faculty of Arts and Sciences</xref>,
<xref target="http://ed.stanford.edu/suse/faculty/dspace.html">Stanford's School of Education</xref>, and other institutions
and faculties. MOspace could even be a home for a new open access journal in the future.</p>

<p>An important part of the MOspace effort is encouraging authors not to sign away rights to their
own works, as often happens when they publish in commercial journals.  Retaining the copyright
allows content to be made available to students and scholars without huge subscription fees. In
MOspace, the author/creator retains copyright in all cases, so an author could also publish an
item elsewhere, providing that the publisher allows (see this
<xref target="http://www.arl.org/sparc/author/completeonline.shtml">author's addendum</xref>
for an example addendum to a publisher's contract).  For items not commercially published, author
permission is all that is needed to allow the Library to add it to MOspace. Library staff can
download items from websites or upload items directly via author submission.  Authors can submit
works directly to <xref target="mailto:mospace@missouri.edu">mospace@missouri.edu</xref>;
most electronic formats are accepted for submission.</p>

<p>Establishing MOspace is part of the crucial role libraries play in preserving research and
scholarship in all forms and making knowledge accessible for future scholars.</p>

<p>For more information, <xref target="../pages/help">consult our help page</xref>, call 573-882-1685, or email <xref target="mailto:mospace@missouri.edu">mospace@missouri.edu</xref>.
To get in touch with a MOspace representative from UMKC, call 816-235-2227 or email <xref target="mospace@umkc.edu">mospace@umkc.edu</xref>.
To contact a Scholars' Mine representative from Missouri S&amp;T, call 573-341-4221 or email <xref target="scholarsmine@mst.edu">scholarsmine@mst.edu</xref>.

</p>

<p>We look forward to receiving your submissions.</p>

<p>
<head>Related</head>
<list n="related" id="file.about.list.related" type="bulleted">
	<item><xref target="http://hdl.handle.net/10355/37875">MOspace Collection Policy</xref></item>
</list>
</p>

</div>
</body>

<meta>
<pageMeta>
<metadata element="title">About MOspace</metadata>
<trail target="../">MOspace Home</trail>
</pageMeta>
</meta>

</document>
