<document xmlns="http://di.tamu.edu/DRI/1.0/" xmlns:i18n="http://apache.org/cocoon/i18n/2.1"
    version="1.1">

    <body>
        <div id="file.about.div.about" n="about" rend="primary">
            <head>About the MOspace Institutional Repository</head>

            <p>The MOspace Institutional Repository is an online repository for creative and
                scholarly works and other resources created by faculty, students, and staff at the
                University of Missouri--Columbia and the University of Missouri--Kansas City. MOspace
                makes these resources freely available on the web and assures their preservation for
                the future.</p>

            <p>MOspace is part of the crucial role libraries play in preserving research and
                scholarship in all forms and making knowledge accessible for future scholars. </p>

            <hi rend="bold">For MU and UMKC Faculty, Students, and Staff</hi>

            <p>MOspace makes your works widely available and provides a permanent URL for ongoing
                access. MOspace fulfills the requirement of many grants for the deposit of research
                data.</p>

            <p>Submitting scholarly work to MOspace offers many benefits:</p>
            
                <list><item>Increased visibility</item>
                    <item>Author retention of copyright</item>
                    <item>Increased citation rates</item>
                    <item>Google search optimization</item>
                    <item>Full-text search and display</item>
                    <item>Perpetual access and preservation</item>
                    <item>Processing by library employees</item></list>
                
                <p>MOspace allows the libraries of the University of Missouri to preserve 
                    and provide open access to items in a more
                    permanent way than posting to a website. The Libraries are committed to this
                    ongoing effort as part of the next generation of library collections.</p>
                
                <hi rend="bold">For Users Worldwide</hi>
                
                <p>For the most part, MOspace resources are available for use to any web user. The
                    exception to this open access is with some theses and dissertations which have
                    been restricted at the authors' requests.</p>
                
                <hi rend="bold">Open Access and Author Rights</hi>
                
                <p>MOspace, in addition to acting as a preservation tool, is our part of the
                    international open access movement. For more information on open access, see the
                    <xref target="www.sparc.arl.org/issues/open-access">SPARC website</xref>.</p>
                
                <p>An important part of the MOspace effort is encouraging authors to retain rights to their 
                    own works; authors often sign away their rights when they publish in 
                    commercial journals. Retaining copyright permits authors to include their works in open access 
                    repositories, making the content available to students and scholars without huge subscription fees. 
                    In MOspace, the author/creator retains copyright in all cases, so an author could also publish
                    an item elsewhere, providing that the publisher allows this.  See the sample
                    <xref target="http://www.arl.org/sparc/author/completeonline.shtml">author's addendum</xref> on the SPARC 
                    website for an example of an addendum to a publisher's contract.</p> 
              
               <hi rend="bold">Adding Your Content</hi>
                <p>For items not commercially published, author permission is all that is needed to
                    allow the Library to add it to MOspace. Library personnel can download items
                    from websites or upload items directly via author submission. Most electronic
                    formats are accepted for submission. See our <xref target="/xmlui/pages/add">help page for adding
                        resources to MOspace</xref> for more information.</p>
                <p>We look forward to receiving your submissions.</p>
            
                <hi rend="bold">Platform</hi>
                <p>The MOspace Institutional Repository uses DSpace, an open source application
                    developed at MIT.</p>
            
            <hi rend="bold">For More Information</hi>
                <p>For more information, consult our <xref target="/xmlui/pages/help">help page</xref>, or 
                    <xref target="/xmlui/pages/contact">Contact Us</xref>.</p>
<hi rend="bold">Additional University of Missouri Online Library Repositories</hi>

<list>
<item><xref target="http://scholarsmine.mst.edu/">Scholars' Mine: Missouri University of Science and Technology</xref></item>
<item><xref target="http://scholarship.law.missouri.edu/">Scholarship Repository (MU Law)</xref></item>
<item><xref target="https://dl.mospace.umsystem.edu/mu/">MU Digital Library</xref></item>
<item><xref target="https://dl.mospace.umsystem.edu/umkc/">UMKC Digital Special Collections</xref></item>
<item><xref target="https://dl.mospace.umsystem.edu/umsl/">UMSL Digital Library</xref></item>
<item><xref target="http://digital.library.umsystem.edu/">UM Digital Library (Legacy system for the University of Missouri)</xref></item>
</list>
               </div>
 
    </body>


    <meta>
        <pageMeta>
            <metadata element="title">About MOspace</metadata>
            <trail target="../">MOspace Home</trail>
        </pageMeta>
    </meta>

</document>
