<document xmlns="http://di.tamu.edu/DRI/1.0/" xmlns:i18n="http://apache.org/cocoon/i18n/2.1" version="1.1">

<body>
<div id="file.add.div.add" n="news" rend="primary">

<head>Submitting Content to VSim</head>

<hi rend="bold">Who may submit content?</hi>

<p>The long-term vision of the project is to build a thriving community of 
    scholars and educators sharing their 3D content and leveraging existing 
    and new academic modeling work for broad educational use through a 
    project repository and archive focused on the real-time explorations of 
    reconstruction of historic urban environments. Contributors must be 
    registered users before they can submit to the archive. (Registration 
    is free.)</p>

<hi rend="bold">User Types</hi>
<p>
    <hi rend="italic">Unregistered User:</hi> Anyone can download VSim and content from the 
    archive without registering as a user.
</p>

<p>
    <hi rend="italic">General User:</hi> Users must be registered in order to upload VSim 
    narratives, embedded resource files, and archival content to the 
    community collections. We encourage the community to share 
    resources and narratives through related repositories. 
</p>

<p>
    <hi rend="italic">Content Contributor/Creator:</hi> General users must request permission 
    to upgrade their account to ‘Content Contributor/Creator’ so that 
    they can submit their own models and projects to the Repository and 
    Archive. Access is granted on a case by case basis by the Digital 
    Library Program and the Institute for Digital Research and 
    Education. Submission requests for models and projects will be 
    vetted for their academic rigor and educational contribution to the 
    community. To request an upgrade, e-mail <xref target="mailto:vsim@library.ucla.edu">vsim@library.ucla.edu</xref> 
    with your full name, institutional affiliation, a short description 
    of the project and/or model (approximately 800 words), and a 
    bibliography of resources that informed the construction of the 
    model and guided the project. Requests may take up to a week to 
    approve.  
</p>

<hi rend="bold">Submitting files</hi>
<p>
    Once registered as Content Contributor/Creators, users can submit a 
    project to the archive. The submission process involves completion 
    of the project metadata form, and uploading a ‘hero’ image to be 
    used as the project thumbnail. Once created, projects can store 
    collections of models, VSim files, and other project related 
    resources. See “File Types” to learn more about what can be stored 
    and shared through the VSim archive. The final steps of the 
    submission process involve licensing agreements for rights and 
    distribution. (We encourage the use of Creative Commons 
    Attribution-NonCommercial-ShareAlike 
    (<xref target="https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-sa/4.0/">CC BY-NC-SA</xref>) license.)
</p>

<p>
    To start your project submission, click the SUBMIT PROJECT button 
    at the top of this page.
</p>

<hi rend="bold">File types</hi>
<p>
    Most electronic formats can be placed in VSim. Project resources 
    are divided into three different collections: Models, Archives, 
    and Submissions.
</p>

<p>
    <hi rend="italic">Models:</hi> The models collections houses VSim 
    file types as well as many popular model file types. The VSim 
    file formats include binary model files (.vsim), individual 
    narrative files (.nar), and individual embedded resource files 
    (.ere). 
</p>

<list n="models" id="file.add.models.list" type="bulleted">
    <item>VSim file types: .vsim, .nar, and .ere </item>
    <item>Other model formats: .flt, .obj, .osg , .osgt, .osgb, .ive, .3ds, .skp</item>
</list>


<p>
    <hi rend="italic">Archives:</hi> The archives collection is for all 
    other project-related files. From project notes, to static images, 
    to final documentation or publication documents, the archive can 
    hold whatever additional files you would like to offer the user 
    community to better understand and utilize your project models. 
    These files can also help other users customize their own VSim 
    narratives and embedded resources for the project model.
</p>

<list n="archives" id="file.add.archives.list" type="bulleted">
    <item>Other resources include: .pdf, .jpeg, .jpg, .tif, .png, .cad, .doc, .docx, .mp4, .mpg, .csv, .ppt, .tar, .zip, .kml (basically any file type that supports your project)</item>
</list>


<hi rend="bold">Contact us</hi>

<p><xref target="/xmlui/pages/contact">Contact us</xref> if you have 
    questions about submitting content, preferred file formats, and 
    inclusion of previously published content in an open access 
    repository.
</p>

</div>

</body>

<meta>
<pageMeta>
<metadata element="title">Submit Works to VSim</metadata>
<trail target="../">VSim Home</trail>
<trail target="#">Submit Works to VSim</trail>
</pageMeta>
</meta>

</document>
