<document xmlns="http://di.tamu.edu/DRI/1.0/" xmlns:i18n="http://apache.org/cocoon/i18n/2.1"
    version="1.1">

    <body>
        <div id="file.about.div.download" n="about" rend="primary">
            <head>VSim Downloads</head>

            <hi rend="bold">The NEH-funded VSim Prototype Version 1</hi>

            <p>The VSim prototype was released in 2013 and three versions of the
              software are currently available. The most recent is VSim 1.2.1
              for Windows. This version can also be used on a dual-boot Mac or
              through Windows emulating software (e.g., Parallels).  There are
              two versions of the original prototype, one for Windows and one
              for Macs. Use these versions of the software if you want to create
              content that can be used interchangeably on Windows and Macs.
              Directions for installing on Windows systems, a sample model of
              the Pantheon, sample narratives, and user guides are provided
              below.</p>

            <p>The VSim team is actively seeking feedback on the software
              prototype. For details about participating in this research,
              please read the VSim_StudyInformationSheet. If you choose to
              provide comments about the software, please use the
              VSim_FeedbackForm or e-mail your thoughts to Lisa M. Snyder
              (lms AT idre DOT ucla DOT edu).</p>

            <list>
            <item><xref target="https://idre.ucla.edu/?wpdmdl=5349">The most recent (v 1.2.1) Windows-compatible release of VSim</xref> (20MB).
            (Please note that content created with this version will not work
            with the Mac-compatible prototype release; opens .dae, .flt. and
            .vsim model files)</item>

            <item><xref target="https://idre.ucla.edu/?wpdmdl=5114">Windows-compatible release</xref> of the original VSim prototype (v 1) with
            a few post-grant additions (20MB). (Opens .dae, .flt, and .vsim
            model files)</item>

            <item><xref target="https://idre.ucla.edu/?wpdmdl=5112">Mac-compatible release</xref> of the original VSim prototype (15MB). (Only
            opens .vsim model files)</item>
            </list>

            <hi rend="bold">The Digital Karnak Publication Prototype</hi>

            <p><xref target="/xmlui/discover?scope=%2F&amp;query=digital+karnak">SEARCH the VSim Repository and Archive for Digital Karnak files</xref></p>

            <p><hi rend="bold">IMPORTANT NOTICE: The posted version of the Digital Karnak
            Publication Prototype has expired! We are working on a new version
            of the file and will post it as soon as possible. Please check back
            to download the new version. If you need a new file immediately for
            a scheduled lecture or presentation, please e-mail Lisa M. Snyder
            (lms AT idre DOT ucla DOT edu).</hi></p>

            <p>VSim was designed so that it could be used as a platform to peer
            review, publish, and broadly disseminate academically generated 3D
            content. A prototype publication focused on the interactive Digital
            Karnak model has been developed and is available below. This package
            features the real-time Digital Karnak model and contains a series of
            narratives that describe the physical changes at Karnak across the
            reigns of eight rulers as well as a suite of embedded resources that
            provide supplementary information for users about the reconstruction
            and the history of the complex. The zip file includes VSim 1.2.1 for
            Windows, a cheat sheet, and a users’ guide.  This file will also
            work on Mac with Windows-emulating software (e.g., Parallels). It
            expired on August 31, 2016.</p>

            <p><hi rend="bold">Video presentation</hi>: <xref target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=IlOnKNhRB5c">Digital Karnak</xref> (a presentation by Elaine A.
            Sullivan and Lisa M. Snyder captured through WebEx; the initial ~42
            minutes is a basic presentation, followed by ~30 minutes of
            discussion).</p>

            <p>If you’ve downloaded the publication prototype and are willing to
            share your thoughts, we’d love to hear from you. The Karnak and VSim
            teams are actively seeking feedback on either the Digital Karnak
            package or the VSim prototype. For details about participating in
            this research, please read the VSim_StudyInformationSheet. If you
            choose to provide comments about the software and/or the model,
            please use the VSim_FeedbackForm (also included in the Digital
            Karnak Package download) or e-mail your thoughts to Lisa M. Snyder
            (lms AT idre DOT ucla DOT edu).</p>

            <p><hi rend="bold">Sample files (models and narratives)</hi></p>


            <list>
              <item><xref target="https://idre.ucla.edu/files/Pantheon_v082.vsim">Sample model of the Pantheon</xref> (a .vsim file) created at UCLA (64MB).</item>
              <item><xref target="https://idre.ucla.edu/files/Pantheon_VSimBasics_March25.nar">A narrative for Windows that works with the Pantheon model and explains the basic features of VSim</xref> (2.4MB)</item>
              <item><xref target="https://idre.ucla.edu/files/Pantheon_Navigation.nar">A narrative for Windows that works with the Pantheon model that explains VSim navigation</xref> (13.5MB)</item>
              <item><xref target="https://idre.ucla.edu/files/Pantheon_CameraMoves4.nar">A narrative for Windows that works with the Pantheon model that describes how to create ‘camera moves’</xref> (1.5MB)</item>
            </list>

            <hi rend="bold">User guides, tutorials, and presentations</hi>

            <list>
              <item><xref target="https://idre.ucla.edu/wp-content/uploads/2015/09/vsim-v1-userguide-june2013.pdf?x83242">Users’ guide</xref> (last updated June 13, 2013).</item>
              <item><xref target="https://idre.ucla.edu/sites/default/files/vsim-v1-graphicguide-july2013.pdf?x83242">Short graphic guide</xref> (last updated July 9, 2013).</item>
              <item><xref target="http://mith.umd.edu/podcasts/a-conversation-about-compulsion/">Digital Dialogues presentation featuring VSim</xref> (MITH: Maryland
                    Institute for Technology in the Humanities, University of Maryland)</item>
              <item><xref target="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=TUz086WMGNU">VSim Tutorial on YouTube</xref> captured at the Humanities Heritage NEH
              Summer Institute (NEH Advanced Topics in the Digital Humanites
                    Summer Institute, The Center for Digital Initiatives, Arkansas
                    State University)</item>
              <item><xref target="http://cdi.astateweb.org/neh/lecturespresentations/">Humanities Heritage 3D Visualization presentation featuring VSim</xref>
                    (NEH Advanced Topics in the Digital Humanites Summer Institute, The
                    Center for Digital Initiatives, Arkansas State University)</item>
            </list>

            <hi rend="bold">Directions for installing the VSim prototype on Windows systems</hi>

            <list rend="numeric" type="ordered">
            <item>Create a VSim folder on your hard drive</item>
            <item>Right click on the links and ‘save link as ...’ the software, sample model, and other files as desired</item>
            <item>Unzip the VSim .zip file (typically a right click, choose WinZip from the menu, and ‘extract to here’)</item>
            <item>Navigate into the release folder and double click the VSim.exe file to launch the software</item>
            <item>If you downloaded the sample files, click File -> Open Model and browse for the Pantheon_v082.vsim file</item>
            <item>Click on File > Import Narrative and browse for the Pantheon_VSimBasics_March25.nar file</item>
            <item>Click on the VSim Basics narrative in the bar across the top of the VSim window and press ‘>’</item>
            <item>When you’re done with that, select and play “The Pantheon” narrative</item>
            <item>Once that tour has completed (at the view of the occulus), press the spacebar to explore the model in WASD mode</item>
            <item>Read the user guide for help loading models and creating narratives of your own! (VSim loads 3D content in .flt, .dae, .vsim, and .ive formats.)</item>
          </list>
            <p>Remember that this software is a prototype. It is a
              proof-of-concept to allow us to assess the educational
              possibilities of three-dimensional content and the functionality
              built into VSim. Please report any reproducible problems to
              Lisa M. Snyder (lms AT idre DOT ucla DOT edu).</p>

               </div>
    </body>


    <meta>
        <pageMeta>
            <metadata element="title">VSim Downloads</metadata>
            <trail target="../">VSim Home</trail>
        </pageMeta>
    </meta>

</document>
