<document xmlns="http://di.tamu.edu/DRI/1.0/" xmlns:i18n="http://apache.org/cocoon/i18n/2.1" version="1.1">

<body>
<div id="file.help.div.help" n="help" rend="primary">
<head>MOspace Help</head>


<div id="top" n="top">
	<list n="toc" id="file.help.list.toc" type="bulleted">
		<item><xref target="#what_is_mospace">What is MOspace?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#why_is_mospace_important">Why is MOspace important?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#how_is_mospace_different">How is MOspace different from a personal website</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#who_can_access_mospace">Who can access MOspace?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#what_are_the_copyright_implications">What are the copyright implications of submitting to MOspace?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#what_types_of_works">What types of works can be included in MOspace?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#how_are_works_collected">How are works collected for MOspace?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#who_can_submit">Who can submit works to MOspace?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#benefits_of_submitting">What are the benefits of submitting works to MOspace?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#how_to_submit">How can I submit works to MOspace?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#how_to_cite">How do I cite something I find in MOspace?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#browse">What do the BROWSE options do?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#search">How do I SEARCH MOspace?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#what_is_searched">What is searched in the general keyword search?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#what_is_not_searched">What is NOT searched (Stop Words)?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#other_search_options">What other options do I have when constructing my search?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#advanced_search">How do I use the Advanced Search form?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#communities">What are Communities?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#collections">What are Collections?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#handles">What are Handles?</xref></item>
	</list>
</div>

<div id="what.is.mospace" n="whatis">
<head>What is MOspace?</head>
<p>
MOspace is the digital institutional repository of the University of Missouri System and is a joint initiative of the University libraries, the Office of Library Systems, and the Division of Information Technology. It is a permanent digital storehouse of research and knowledge focusing on works created by those connected with the University of Missouri.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="why.is.mospace.important" n="whyimportant">
<head>Why is MOspace important?</head>
<p>
MOspace acts as a preservation tool and contributes to the international open access movement. Recent votes in favor of open access have passed in many institutions, including Harvard's Faculty of Arts and Sciences, Stanford's School of Education.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="how.is.mospace.different" n="howdifferent">
<head>How is MOspace different from a personal website?</head>
<p>
MOspace allows the library to preserve and provide open access to the items in a more permanent way than posting to a website. The use of DSpace software, an open source product developed at MIT, provides permanent URLs for documents deposited through it to the MOspace server.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="who.can.access.mospace" n="whoaccess">
<head>Who can access MOspace?</head>
<p>
MOspace is open access, meaning anyone can view it from the open web. By providing free access to a rich body of work, MOspace promotes research and knowledge produced by the University of Missouri.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="what.are.the.copyright.implications" n="copyright">
<head>What are the copyright implications of submitting to MOspace?</head>
<p>
MOspace encourages authors not to sign away rights to their own works, as often happens when they publish in commercial journals.  Retaining the copyright allows content to be made available to students and scholars without huge subscription fees.  In MOspace, the author/creator retains copyright in all cases, so an author could also publish an item elsewhere, providing that the publisher allows (see this <xref target="http://www.arl.org/sparc/author/completeonline.shtml">author's addendum</xref> for an example addendum to a publisher's contract).  For items not commercially published, author permission is all that is needed to allow the Library to add it to MOspace.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="what.types.of.works" n="typesofworks">
<head>What types of works can be included in MOspace?</head>
<p>
MOspace includes, but is not limited to, the following content types:
<list n="filetypes" id="file.help.list.filetypes" type="bulleted">
	<item>Audio and visual materials</item>
	<item>Committee and task force reports</item>
	<item>Conference papers, presentations and proceedings</item>
	<item>Course materials and learning objects</item>
	<item>Creative works</item>
	<item>Data sets</item>
	<item>Digital art</item>
	<item>Journals published on the campus</item>
	<item>Manuscripts</item>
	<item>Organizational annual reports and newsletters</item>
	<item>Pre-prints</item>
	<item>Published and unpublished papers, articles, chapters and books</item>
	<item>Theses and dissertations</item>
	<item>Undergraduate research papers</item>
	<item>Working papers and technical reports</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="how.are.works.collected" n="howcollected">
<head>How are works collected for MOspace?</head>
<p>
Faculty, staff and students are encouraged to submit works directly. Staff members of the MU libraries collect works in two ways. They can download items from websites or upload items directly via author submission.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="who.can.submit" n="whosubmit">
<head>Who can submit works to MOspace?</head>
<p>
Faculty, staff, students, and other individuals or entities affiliated or associated with the University of Missouri can submit. Works co-authored by those not affiliated with the university are accepted.  If you have any question, email <xref target="mailto:mospace@missouri.edu">mospace@missouri.edu</xref>
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="benefits.of.submitting" n="benefits">
<head>What are the benefits of submitting works to MOspace?</head>
<p>
MOspace provides content with increased visibility, a permanent URL, a dedication to preservation, and full-text searchability. Establishing MOspace is part of the crucial role libraries play in making knowledge accessible for a wider audience and preserving research and scholarship for future scholars. The
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="how.to.submit" n="howtosubmit">
<head>How can I submit works to MOspace?</head>
<p>
Authors associated the campuses in Columbia, Kansas City and St. Louis can submit works directly to <xref target="mailto:mospace@missouri.edu">mospace@missouri.edu</xref> or call 573-882-1685 for additional Information. Authors associated with the Missouri University of Science and Technology should visit the <xref target="http://libguides.mst.edu/content.php?pid=362942">Submitting Content section of the Library Guide to Scholars’ Mine</xref>, email <xref target="mailto:scholarsmine@mst.edu">scholarsmine@mst.edu</xref> or call 573-334-4221 for additional information. 
</p>
<p>
PDF is the preferred format for documents, but most electronic formats are accepted for submission. We look forward to receiving your submissions.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>


<div id="how.to.cite" n="howtocite">
<head>How do I cite something I find in MOspace?</head>
<p>
Each item in MOspace has been assigned a "<xref target="#handles">handle</xref>," a persistent URL you can use when citing the item in publications or other communications. In most citation styles, you'll treat the MOspace item as an electronic publication.
</p>
<p>
For example:
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">APA Style</hi>: Schlicher, M. A. (2008). Biofuels in the US: Today and in the future. AgBioForum, 11, 1-7. Retrieved from http://hdl.handle.net/10355/32.
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Chicago Style</hi>: Schlicher, Martha A. "Biofuels in the US: Today and in the Future." AgBioForum 11 (2008): 1-7, http://hdl.handle.net/10355/32.
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">MLA Style</hi>: Schlicher, Martha A. "Biofuels in the US: Today and in the Future." AgBioForum 11.1 (2008): 1-7. 24 Feb. 2009 &lt;http://hdl.handle.net/10355/32&gt;.
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Vancouver Style</hi>: Schlicher MA. Biofules in the US: today and in the future. AgBioForum 2008;11(1):1-7. Available from http://hdl.handle.net/10355/32.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>














<div id="browse" n="browse">
<head>What do the BROWSE options do?</head>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Browse</hi> allows you to go through a list of items in some specified order:
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Browse by Community/Collection</hi> takes you through the communities in alphabetical order and allows you to see the subcommunities and collections within each community.
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Browse by Title</hi> allows you to move through an alphabetical list of all titles of items in MOspace.
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Browse by Author</hi> allows you to move through an alphabetical list of all authors of items in MOspace.
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Browse by Subject</hi> allows you to move through an alphabetical list of subjects assigned to items in MOspace.
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Browse by Date</hi> allows you to move through a list of all items in MOspace in reverse chronological order.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>


<div id="search" n="search">
<head>How do I SEARCH MOspace?</head>
<p>
To search all of MOspace, use the search box at the top of the navigation bar on the left (or the search box in the middle of the home page).
</p>
<p>
<figure source="../static/images/help/searchtop.gif" />
</p>
<p>
To limit your search to a specific community or collection, navigate to that community or collection and use the search bar on that page.
</p>
<p>
<figure source="../static/images/help/searchother.gif" />
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="what.is.searched" n="whatissearched">
<head>What is searched in the general keyword search?</head>
<p>
MOspace uses the <xref target="http://lucene.apache.org/java/docs/">Apache Lucene</xref> search engine. Here are some search hints:
</p>
<p>
The word(s) you enter in the search box will be searched against the title, author, subject abstract, series, sponsor and identifier fields of each item's record.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>


<div id="what.is.not.searched" n="whatissearched">
<head>What is NOT searched (Stop Words)?</head>
<p>
The search engine ignores certain words that occur frequently in English, but do not add value to the search. These are:
</p>
<p>
"a", "and" , "are" , "as" , "at" , "be" , "but" , "by" , "for" , "if" , "in" , "into",
</p>
<p>
"is" ,"it" ,"no" , "not" , "of" , "on" , "or" , "such", "the" , "to" , "was"
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>


<div id="other.search.options" n="otheroptions">
<head>What other options do I have when constructing my search?</head>

<p><hi rend="bold">Truncation</hi> - Use an asterisk (*) after a word stem to get all hits having words starting with that root, for example:</p>
<p><figure source="../static/images/help/search1.gif"> select* </figure></p>
<p>will retrieve selects, selector, selectman, selecting.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Stemming</hi> - The search engine automatically expands words with common endings to include plurals, past tenses ...etc.</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Phrase Searching</hi> - To search using multiple words as a phrase, put quotation marks (") around the phrase.</p>

<p><figure source="../static/images/help/search8.jpg"> "organizational change" </figure></p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Exact word match</hi> - Put a plus (+) sign before a word if it MUST appear in the search result. For instance, in the following search the word "training" is optional, but the word "dog" must be in the result.
</p>
<p><figure source="../static/images/help/search2.gif"> +dog training </figure></p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Eliminate items with unwanted words</hi> - Put a minus (-) sign before a word if it should not appear in the search results. Alternatively, you can use NOT. This can limit your search to eliminate unwanted hits. For instance, in the search
</p>
<p><figure source="../static/images/help/search3.jpg"> training -cat </figure> or <figure source="../static/images/help/search4.jpg"> training NOT cat </figure></p>

<p>you will get items containing the word "training", except those that also contain the word "cat".</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">Boolean searching</hi> - The following Boolean operators can be used to combine terms. Note that they must be CAPITALIZED !</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">AND</hi> - to limit searches to find items containing all words or phrases combined with this operator, e.g.</p>
<p><figure source="../static/images/help/search5.jpg"> cats AND dogs </figure></p>
<p>will retrieve all items that contain BOTH the words "cats" and "dogs".</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">OR</hi> - to enlarge searches to find items containing any of the words or phrases surrounding this operator</p>
<p><figure source="../static/images/help/search6.jpg"> cats OR dogs </figure></p>
<p> will retrieve all items that contain EITHER the words "cats" or "dogs".</p>

<p><hi rend="bold">NOT</hi> - to exclude items containing the word following this operator, e.g.</p>
<p><figure source="../static/images/help/search4.jpg"> training NOT cat </figure></p>
<p>will retrieve all items that contain the word "training" EXCEPT those also containing the word "cat".</p>

<p>Parentheses can be used in the search query to group search terms into sets, and operators can then be applied to the whole set, e.g. </p>
<p><figure source="../static/images/help/search7.jpg"> (cats OR dogs) AND (training OR discipline) </figure></p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>


<div id="advanced.search" n="advancedsearch">
<head>How do I use the Advanced Search form?</head>
<p>
The advanced search page allows you to specify the fields you wish to search, and to combine these searches with the Boolean "and", "or" or "not".
</p>
<p>
You can restrict your search to a community by clicking on the arrow to the right of the top box. If you want your search to encompass all of DSpace, leave that box in the default position.
</p>
<p>
Then select the field to search in the left hand column and enter the word or phrase you are searching in the right hand column. You can select the Boolean operator to combine searches by clicking on the arrow to the right of the "AND" box.
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Note: You must use the input boxes in order. If you leave the first one blank your search will not work.</hi>
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>


<div id="communities" n="communities">
<head>What are Communities?</head>
<p>
MOspace content is organized around Communities which can correspond to administrative entities such as schools, departments, labs and research centers. Within each community there can be an unlimited number subcommunities and an unlimited number of collections. Each collection may contain an unlimited number of items. This organization gives MOspace the flexibility to accommodate differing needs of communities by allowing them to
</p>
<p>
<list n="communityitems" id="file.help.list.community.items" type="bulleted">
	<item>Decide on policies such as
		<list n="communitypolicies" id="file.help.list.community.policies" type="bulleted">
			<item>who contributes content</item>
			<item>whether there will be a review process</item>
			<item>who will have access</item>
		</list>
	</item>
	<item>Determine workflow - reviewing, editing, metadata</item>
	<item>Manage collections</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>
Each community has its own entry page displaying information, news and links reflecting the interests of that community, as well as a descriptive list of collections within the community.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>


<div id="collections" n="collections">
<head>What are Collections?</head>
<p>
Communities can maintain an unlimited number of collections in MOspace. Collections can be organized around a topic, or by type of information (such as working papers or datasets) or by any other sorting method a community finds useful in organizing its digital items. Collections can have different policies and workflows.
</p>
<p>
Each MOspace collection has its own entry page displaying information, news and links reflecting the interests of users of that collection.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>


<div id="handles" n="handles">
<head>What are Handles?</head>
<p>
When your item becomes a part of the MOspace repository it is assigned a persistent URL. This means that, unlike most URLs, this identifier will not have to be changed when the system migrates to new hardware, or when changes are made to the system. MOspace is committed to maintaining the integrity of this identifier so that you can safely use it to refer to your item when citing it in publications or other communications. Our persistent urls are registered with the <xref target="http://www.handle.net/">Handle System</xref>, a comprehensive system for assigning, managing, and resolving persistent identifiers, known as "handles," for digital objects and other resources on the Internet. The Handle System is administered by the <xref target="http://www.cnri.reston.va.us/">Corporation for National Research Initiatives (CNRI)</xref>, which undertakes, fosters, and promotes research in the public interest.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>







</div>
</body>

<meta>
<pageMeta>
<metadata element="title">MOspace Help</metadata>
<trail target="../">MOspace Home</trail>
</pageMeta>
</meta>

</document>
