<document xmlns="http://di.tamu.edu/DRI/1.0/" xmlns:i18n="http://apache.org/cocoon/i18n/2.1" version="1.1">

<body>
<div id="file.help.div.help" n="help" rend="primary">
<head>MOspace Institutional Repository Help</head>

<div id="top" n="top">
<head>
About the MOspace Institutional Repository
</head>
	<list n="toc" id="file.help.list.toc" type="bulleted">
		<item><xref target="#what_is_mospace">What is MOspace?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#why_is_mospace_important">Why is MOspace important?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#how_is_mospace_different">How is MOspace different from a personal website</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#who_can_access_mospace">Who can access MOspace?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#what_types_of_works">What types of works can be included in MOspace?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#how_are_works_collected">How are works collected for MOspace?</xref></item>
	</list>
<head>
Submitting content to the MOspace Institutional Repository
</head>
	<list n="toc" id="file.help.list.toc" type="bulleted">
		<item><xref target="#who_can_submit">Who can submit works to MOspace?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#benefits_of_submitting">What are the benefits of submitting works to MOspace?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#what_are_the_copyright_implications">What are the copyright implications of submitting to MOspace?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#how_to_submit">How can I submit works to MOspace?</xref></item>
	</list>
<head>
Using the MOspace Institutional Repository
</head>
	<list n="toc" id="file.help.list.toc" type="bulleted">
		<item><xref target="#how_to_cite">How do I cite something I find in MOspace?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#search">How do I SEARCH MOspace?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#browse">What do the BROWSE options do?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#what_is_searched">What is searched in the general keyword search?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#what_is_not_searched">What is NOT searched (Stop Words)?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#other_search_options">What other options do I have when constructing my search?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#advanced_search">How do I use the Advanced Search form?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#communities">What are Communities and Collections?</xref></item>
		<item><xref target="#handles">What are Handles?</xref></item>
	</list>
</div>
<head>
About the MOspace Institutional Repository
</head>
<div id="what.is.mospace" n="whatis">
<p rend="bold">What is MOspace?</p>
<p>
The MOspace Institutional Repository is an online repository for creative and scholarly works and other resources created by faculty, students, and staff at the University of Missouri—Columbia and the University of Missouri—Kansas City.  MOspace makes these resources freely available on the web and assures their preservation for the future.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="why.is.mospace.important" n="whyimportant">
<p rend="bold">Why is MOspace important?</p>
<p>
The MOspace Institutional Repository acts as a preservation tool and contributes to the international open access movement.  MOspace is our part of the international open access movement.  For more information on open access, see <xref target="http://www.sparc.arl.org/issues/open-access">the SPARC website</xref>.
</p>
<p>
An important part of the MOspace effort is encouraging authors not to sign away rights to their own works, as often happens when they publish in commercial journals. Retaining the copyright allows content to be made available to students and scholars without huge subscription fees. In MOspace, the author/creator retains copyright in all cases, so an author could also publish an item elsewhere, providing that the publisher allows (see this <xref target="http://www.sparc.arl.org/resource/complete-sparc-author-addendum-online">author's addendum</xref> on the SPARC website for an example addendum to a publisher's contract). 
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="how.is.mospace.different" n="howdifferent">
<p rend="bold">How is MOspace different from a personal website?</p>
<p>
MOspace allows the library to preserve and provide open access to the items in a more permanent way than posting to a website. The use of DSpace software, an open source product developed at MIT, provides permanent URLs for resources.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="who.can.access.mospace" n="whoaccess">
<p rend="bold">Who can access MOspace?</p>
<p>
MOspace is open access, meaning anyone can view it from the open web. By providing free access to a rich body of work, MOspace promotes research and knowledge produced by the University of Missouri.
</p>
<p>
Use of resources is guided by a license for each item.  The MOspace default license is a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License (CC BY-NC-ND).  The full legal codes of Creative Commons licenses are available at: https://creativecommons.org/licenses/.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="what.types.of.works" n="typesofworks">
<p rend="bold">What types of works can be included in MOspace?</p>
<p>
MOspace includes, but is not limited to, the following content types:
<list n="filetypes" id="file.help.list.filetypes" type="bulleted">
	<item>Audio and visual materials</item>
	<item>Committee and task force reports</item>
	<item>Conference papers, presentations and proceedings</item>
	<item>Course materials and learning objects</item>
	<item>Creative works</item>
	<item>Data sets</item>
	<item>Digital art</item>
	<item>Journals published on the campus</item>
	<item>Manuscripts</item>
	<item>Organizational annual reports and newsletters</item>
	<item>Pre-prints</item>
	<item>Published and unpublished papers, articles, chapters and books</item>
	<item>Theses and dissertations</item>
	<item>Undergraduate research papers</item>
	<item>Working papers and technical reports</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="how.are.works.collected" n="howcollected">
<p rend="bold">How are works collected for MOspace?</p>
<p>
We download items from websites or upload items directly via author submission.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>
<head>
Submitting content to the MOspace Institutional Repository
</head>
<div id="who.can.submit" n="whosubmit">
<p rend="bold">Who can submit works to MOspace?</p>
<p>
Faculty, students, staff, and other individuals or entities associated with the University of Missouri—Columbia, the University of Missouri—Kansas City, and the University of Missouri System are encouraged to submit works to MOspace.  Co-authors need not be affiliated with the University of Missouri. 
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="benefits.of.submitting" n="benefits">
<p rend="bold">What are the benefits of submitting works to MOspace?</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">For Faculty, Students, and Staff</hi>

MOspace makes your works widely available and provides a permanent URL for ongoing access.  MOspace fulfills the requirement of many grants for the deposit of research data.</p>  
<p>
Submitting scholarly work to MOspace offers many benefits:
<list n="filetypes" id="file.help.list.filetypes" type="bulleted">
	<item>Increased visibility</item>
	<item>Author retention of copyright</item>
	<item>Increased citation rates</item>
	<item>Google search optimization</item>
	<item>Full-text search and display</item>
	<item>Perpetual access and preservation</item>
	<item>Processing by library employees</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>
MOspace allows the library to preserve and provide open access to items in a more permanent way than posting to a website.  The Libraries are committed to this ongoing effort as part of the next generation of library collections.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">For Users Worldwide</hi>
</p>
<p>
For the most part, MOspace resources are available for use to any web user.  The exception to open access is with some theses and dissertations which have been restricted at the authors’ requests.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="what.are.the.copyright.implications" n="copyright">
<p rend="bold">What are the copyright implications of submitting to MOspace?</p>
<p>
MOspace encourages authors not to sign away rights to their own works, as often happens when they publish in commercial journals.  Retaining the copyright allows content to be made available to students and scholars without huge subscription fees.  In MOspace, if you are the copyright holder, you retain the copyright in all cases, so that you can publish elsewhere, providing that the publisher allows such publishing.  See this <xref target="http://www.arl.org/sparc/author/completeonline.shtml">author's addendum</xref> on the SPARC website for an example addendum to a publisher's contract.  For items not commercially published, author permission is all that is needed to allow us to add it to MOspace.
</p>
<p>
The default license used in MOspace is a Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivs License (CC BY-NC-ND).  The full legal codes of Creative Commons licenses are available at: https://creativecommons.org/licenses/.  You may choose to submit a different license.  Consult with your campus <xref target="mospace@missouri.edu">MOspace manager</xref> to discuss license options.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="how.to.submit" n="howtosubmit">
<p rend="bold">How can I submit works to MOspace?</p>
<p>
See <xref target="https://mospace.umsystem.edu/xmlui/pages/add">Submitting Content to MOspace</xref>. 
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="how.to.cite" n="howtocite">
<p rend="bold">How do I cite something I find in MOspace?</p>
<p>
Each item in MOspace has been assigned a "<xref target="https://irsandbox.lso.umsystem.edu/xmlui/pages/help#handles">handle</xref>," a persistent URL you can use when citing the item in publications or other communications. In most citation styles, you'll treat the MOspace item as an electronic publication.
</p>
<p>
For example:
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">APA Style:</hi> Schlicher, M. A. (2008). Biofuels in the US: Today and in the future. AgBioForum, 11, 1-7. Retrieved from http://hdl.handle.net/10355/32.
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Chicago Style:</hi> Schlicher, Martha A. "Biofuels in the US: Today and in the Future." AgBioForum 11 (2008): 1-7, http://hdl.handle.net/10355/32.
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">MLA Style:</hi> Schlicher, Martha A. "Biofuels in the US: Today and in the Future." AgBioForum 11.1 (2008): 1-7. 24 Feb. 2009 &lt;http://hdl.handle.net/10355/32&gt;.
</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">Vancouver Style:</hi> Schlicher MA. Biofules in the US: today and in the future. AgBioForum 2008;11(1):1-7. Available from http://hdl.handle.net/10355/32.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>
<head>
Using the MOspace Institutional Repository
</head>
<div id="search" n="search">
<p rend="bold">How do I search MOspace?</p>
<p>
You have more than one option. You may use a keyword search, which will search for the words you enter anywhere in the indexed fields. If you have a specific title or author, try a browse search.  The word(s) you enter will be searched from the beginning of indexed fields.  Keyword searches are a useful way to start if you don’t have a specific author or title in mind or aren’t sure of the author’s name or the exact title. These two types of searches are discussed in more detail below.
</p>
<p>
To limit your search to a specific community or collection, navigate to that community or collection and use the search bar on that page.  
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="browse" n="browse">
<p rend="bold">What do the BROWSE options do?</p>
<p>
Browse allows you to retrieve a list of items in alphabetical or numerical order.  The words you enter in the search box are searched from the beginning from fields in MOspace and in the order you enter them.  From the browse results screen you can jump to a spot in the list by typing in the first few letters of your text string or by choosing an option in the menu of letters of the alphabet.  
</p>
<p>
Browse options are available for:
<list n="filetypes" id="file.help.list.filetypes" type="bulleted">
	<item>Community/Collection</item>
	<item>Date Issued</item>
	<item>Author – For personal names, search the last name first:  Smith, John</item>
	<item>Author/Contribution – For personal names, search the last name first:  Smith, John</item>
	<item>Title</item>
	<item>Subject</item>
	<item>Identifier</item>
	<item>Thesis Department</item>
	<item>Thesis Advisor</item>
	<item>Thesis Semester</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="what.is.searched" n="whatissearched">
<p rend="bold">What is searched in the general keyword SEARCH?</p>
<p>
With a keyword search, the words you enter will be found where ever they appear in a field.  The word(s) you enter in the search box will be searched against the following metadata fields:
<list n="filetypes" id="file.help.list.filetypes" type="bulleted">
	<item>Communities and collections</item>
	<item>Date Issued</item>
	<item>Creators and contributors, including authors, editors, and illustrators</item>
	<item>Author/Contribution – For personal names, search the last name first:  Smith, John</item>
	<item>Corporate names and meeting names</item>
	<item>Names of sponsor</item>
	<item>Dates (copyright, created, issued, submitted for theses)</item>
	<item>Abstracts</item>
	<item>Tables of contents</item>
	<item>Related works</item>
	<item>Subjects</item>
	<item>Thesis departments</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>MOspace uses the <xref target="http://lucene.apache.org/core/">Apache Lucene</xref> search engine.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="advanced.search" n="advancedsearch">
<p rend="bold">How do I use ADVANCED SEARCH?</p>
<p>
You will find three options on the Advanced Search page.  All of these allow you to search for a single word or multiple words.  Your options:
<list n="filetypes" id="file.help.list.filetypes" type="numbered">
	<item>Search by keywords in full-text of items plus many of the metadata fields in the records.  You may limit this search by a campus.</item>
	<item>Search by keyword, as above, and include limits under Keyword Search by Field.  View these options by selecting, “[+] Search or Limit by Field.”</item>
	<item>Search for words in specific fields.  Access this option by selecting, “[+] Search or Limit Field.”</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>The third option allows you to specify the field you wish to search and to include multiple fields in one search.  The searches are keyword searches; the text you enter will be used to retrieve items in which those words anywhere in the fields you select.  You also may choose to include words that you do not want to appear, by choosing, “Does Not Contain.”  This will help to exclude items that are not relevant to the results you want.
</p>
<p>Fields available in Advanced Search:
<list n="filetypes" id="file.help.list.filetypes" type="bulleted">
	<item>Title</item>
	<item>Author/Contributor</item>
	<item>Subject</item>
	<item>Subject:Place</item>
	<item>Date Issued (year)</item>
	<item>Sponsor</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>After selecting a field, indicate whether the results should include the text (Contains) or exclude the text (Does Not Contains).  Use the plus sign to add additional fields in your search.</p>
<p>
<hi rend="bold">You must click on a “Search” button to execute the search.</hi>
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="what.is.not.searched" n="whatissearched">
<p rend="bold">What words are NOT searched in a keyword search (Stop Words)?</p>
<p>
The search engine ignores certain words that occur frequently in English, but do not add value to the search. These are:
<list n="filetypes" id="file.help.list.filetypes" type="bulleted">
	<item>a, an, and, are, as, at, be, but, by, for, if, in, into, is, it, no, not, of, on, or, such, that, the, their, then, there, these, they, this, to, was, will, with</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="other.search.options" n="otheroptions">
<p rend="bold">How do I limit search results and use facets</p>
<p>
MOspace uses facets to modify search results in the institutional repository.  You will see the different enabled facets displayed in a "Discover" section in your sidebar, by default, right below the Browse options. Applying a facet normally reduces the original search results. Many facets can be applied on the home page but generally they are applied after an initial search. Facets show counts for each value and allow the user to "drill down" or further restrict their search results based on those facets</p>
<p>Our sidebar facets are:
<list n="filetypes" id="file.help.list.filetypes" type="bulleted">
	<item>Format</item>
	<item>Subject</item>
	<item>Date Issued</item>
	<item>Author</item>
	<item>Author/Contributor</item>
	<item>Subect: Time Period</item>
	<item>Subject: Place</item>
	<item>Advisor</item>
	<item>Thesis Department</item>
	<item>Thesis Semester</item>
	<item>Language</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>
It's important to know that multiple metadata fields can be included in one facet. An important feature of the facets is that their contents are automatically updated based on the context of the page.
</p>
<p>
When using a keyword search in Advanced Search, you can limit your search results using the options under “Keyword search by field.”  On the Advanced Search page, you can access these by choosing, “Search or Limit by Field.”  This gives you the option to search for or exclude words in selected fields.  After executing a keyword search, you can further limit the search results by using facets, as described above.
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>

<div id="communities" n="communities">
<p rend="bold">What are Communities and Collections?</p>
<p>
MOspace content is organized around Communities and Sub-communities which correspond to administrative units such as schools, departments, labs, and research centers. Content in these are organized under collections. Communities, Sub-communities, and Collections have an entry page that may include information on that community or collection.  
</p>
<p>
Collections can be organized around a topic, or by type of information (such as working papers or datasets) or by any other sorting method a community finds useful in organizing its digital items.
</p>

<div id="handles" n="handles">
<p rend="bold">What are Handles?</p>
<p>
MOspace items have persistent URLs.  There URLs are considered persistent, because they are registered with the <xref target="http://www.handle.net/">Handle System</xref>, a comprehensive system for assigning, managing, and resolving persistent identifiers. The use of handles means that, unlike most URLs, this identifier will not have to be changed when the system migrates to new hardware, or when changes are made to the system. 
</p>
<p>You will note that each item has two URLs associated with it.  Use the handle to ensure persistence.
<list n="filetypes" id="file.help.list.filetypes" type="bulleted">
	<item>Regular URL:  https://mospace.umsystem.edu/xmlui/handle/10355/8680</item>
	<item>Handle:  http://hdl.handle.net/10355/8680</item>
</list>
The Handle System is administered by the <xref target="http://www.cnri.reston.va.us/">Corporation for National Research Initiatives (CNRI)</xref>, which undertakes, fosters, and promotes research in the public interest.
</p>
<p>
MOspace is committed to maintaining the integrity of this identifier so that you can safely use it to refer to your item when citing it in publications or other communications. 
</p>
<p>[ <xref target="#top">back to top</xref> ]</p>
</div>


</div>
</body>

<meta>
<pageMeta>
<metadata element="title">MOspace Help</metadata>
<trail target="../">MOspace Home</trail>
</pageMeta>
</meta>

</document>
